Alright בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is נ, nun, and
we pick up on the משנה Mishnah two lines from the bottom
of מ''ט ע''ב, Mem Tet Amud Bet, dealing with a series of
משניות Mishnayot which are, you know, everything that
is A is B but there are things that are B that
aren't A.
And the last one we just read, which was at the end
of yesterday, which was something very challenging, we're talking about people that
can be judges for civil cases and not for capital cases, and
it disqualified people who we would have a hard time understanding why
they should be disqualified at all based on basically ancestry or birth.
And the next משנה Mishnah also raises serious questions, so let's take
a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. כל הכשר לדון כשר להעיד
ויש שכשיר להעיד ואינו כשר לדון. Kol hakasher ladun kasher lehachid veyesh
shekasher lehachid ve’eino kasher ladun. Anybody that can be a judge can
be a
witness, and there are people that can be witnesses that cannot be
judges. So who is that? לאתויי מאי, le’atuyei mai, what is this
coming to include? In fact I should mention something, that in all
these משניות Mishnayot the גמרא Gemara basically says לאתויי מאי, le’atuyei mai,
but לאתויי מאי le’atuyei mai is actually a phrase that's normally used
like when it's not the main point but you're saying something else
that this little thing comes to include, you know, something as well.
Here it's really asking what's the main point of the משנה? Mishnah?
What is the case being referred to that is, you know, that
can be a good witness but not a good judge? So the
phrase לאתויי מאי le’atuyei mai is a little funny in that context.
But anyway, so what is the case that can be a good
witness and not be a good judge? So אמר רבי יוחנן Amar
Rabbi Yochanan לאתויי סומא באחת מעיניו, le’atuyei suma be’achat me’einav, somebody who
is blind in one eye. Somebody who is blind in two eyes
obviously cannot be a witness, it says או ראה, o ra’ah, you
have to see. So interestingly even if you were to just testify
about something that you heard, if you're blind you cannot. Now you
could say that it's a formal exclusion, או ראה, o ra’ah, but
also you can
understand—now again ברוך השם Baruch Hashem I'm not blind so I don't
know—but I can understand the concern at least from people with sight
that if all you have is your ability to hear you might
not accurately be interpreting what exactly are the events that are going
on around you. Certainly most of the information that we absorb from
the outside world is through sight and not through the other senses.
So if you do not have full sight, if you do not
have sight at all, then a person cannot be a witness even
based on things that he might have heard. But presumably even if
you have sight in one eye it is sufficient. Now that I
would say is a חידוש chidush because you could also say, you
know, that without depth perception and sight in only one eye maybe
also it leads to a certain amount of inaccuracy. Nevertheless you are
allowed to be a good witness but you can't be a good
judge. And again this is somewhat ironic, right, because you would say
a judge you're not directly seeing the events, and maybe a little
bit you have to see the witnesses and see the claimants in
order to be judging body language or whatever, but certainly you would
think the ability to see is of a lesser demand for a
judge than for a witness. And nevertheless we're saying that
a witness can be sight in one eye but a judge cannot.
ומני, umani, and this again like yesterday seems like a relatively arbitrary
exclusion. Who is this going like? This is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
היא רבי מאיר, Hi Rabbi Meir, דתניא, detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: Braitah: היה רבי מאיר אומר Haya Rabbi Meir omer מה תלמוד
לומר mah talmud lomar על פיהם יהיה כל ריב וכל נגע? al
pihem yehiyeh kol riv vechol naga?
What is meant by the verse that says by their mouth it
shall be, you know, by the כהנים, kohanim, all judgment and all
wounds—or all נגע nega is often used by חז''ל Chazal to be
understood to mean נגע צרעת, nega tzara'at, leprosy. וכי מה עניין ריבים
אצל נגעים? vechi mah inyan rivim etzel naga’im? What's the point of
mentioning sort of disputes, presumably legal disputes, juxtaposed to looking at צרעת?
tzara'at? מקיש ריבים לנגעים, makish rivim lenaga’im,
to make a link. מה נגעים ביום, mah naga’im bayom, the same
way you can only look at spots of צרעת tzara'at during the
day, דכתיב וביום הראות בו, dechtiv uveyom hira'ot bo, and the day
that it appears the living
flesh he shall be טמא. tamei. So it's that we learn out
as a general rule that you can only look at them during
the day, which makes a good deal of sense, especially in a
period of non-artificial light, the ability to see something accurately would have
to be done at the daytime. But again it's not just a
question of accuracy, it's understood as a formal requirement.
A כהן kohen cannot make a judgment about צרעת tzara'at during the
night, only during the day. So the juxtaposition tells you אף ריבים
ביום, af rivim bayom, similarly when it comes to dealing with disputes
it can only be during the day, you can only have court
cases in the day. We learned that's הלכה, halacha, that court cases
can only be in the day. Now sometimes you can start in
the day and end in the night depending if it's דיני ממונות,
dinei mamonot, דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, whatever, but the general rule is
that it has to be in the day. ומה נגעים שלא בסומא,
umah naga’im shelo besuma, and the same way when it comes to
looking at spots of צרעת tzara'at it cannot be blind, and here
meaning even blind in one eye, דכתיב לכל מראה עיני הכהן, dechtiv
lechol marei einei hakohen, to—right—to the entire vision of the eyes as
Michael says correctly, לכל מראה, lechol marei, the entire, you know, sort
of field of vision, and עיני einei the eyes of the כהן
kohen has to have full sight in order to look at a
נגע. nega. אף ריבים שלא בסומא, af rivim shelo besuma, similarly when
dealing with cases of disputants of legal
disputes. All cases of
dispute and all cases of
צרעת Tzara'at *tzara'at* meaning they are in the position of authority. They
are the ones that are ruling over them.
So let's say you're colorblind. You don't have לכל מראה *le-chol mareh*.
Yeah, but the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* does not seem for looking
at מראות *maros* it's definitely an issue, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
never goes that far in terms of if
the כהנים *Kohanim* can't stand as judges.
So that was the question I was waiting for which is why
is that being assigned to the כהנים *Kohanim* and the reality here
is that in the תורה Torah *Torah*, the role that eventually devolves
around on חזל Chazal, *Chazal* was in the time of the תורה
Torah *Torah* and presumably through the period of the בית המקדש *Beit
HaMikdash* until near the end of the second בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*
was assigned to the כהנים *Kohanim*. They were the class of people
that dealt with teaching תורה Torah *Torah*, ruling over things. You see
that right? What does it say for example in וזאת הברכה *Vezot
HaBerachah*? It says יורו משפטיך ליעקב ותורתך לישראל *yoru mishpatecha le-Ya'akov ve-Toratecha
le-Yisrael*. They were the ones that were supposed to be spread out
throughout the people teaching the תורה *Torah*. And what does it say
when it says you bring a case to the
כהן Kohen *Kohen* at the beginning of שופטים Shoftim *Shoftim*? It says
ובאת אל המקום אשר יבחר השם אלקיך *u-vata el hamakom asher yivchar
Hashem Elokecha* ובאת אל הכהנים הלוים ואל השפט אשר יהיה בימים ההם
*u-vata el hakohanim haleviyim ve-el hashoftet asher yiheyeh bayamim hahem*, right? When
it says you come to the high court, it says you come
to the כהנים *Kohanim*, the לוים *Leviyim* and to the judge in
singular. But fundamentally the כהנים *Kohanim* and לוים *Leviyim*. So while it
may be recognized that there were some other people associated with it,
that role was fundamentally the role of the class of כהנים *Kohanim*
and לוים *Leviyim*. During the end of the second בית המקדש *Beit
HaMikdash* and certainly after the second בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* was destroyed,
that role
their status in terms of the religious authorities of the people for
all
issues was certainly at the end of the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*
but it was shifting even there that it was limited to the
Temple and the class of the rabbis was growing in the period
of the second בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* and ultimately that shifted to
the rabbis. So yes it is interesting we are on the one
hand acknowledging that the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* is invoking both the כהנים
*Kohanim* but there's an implicit assumption that now we know that this
other role is taken over by the rabbis. But even though we
know this other role what? Well no, not looking at נגעים Nega'im
*nega'im*. Looking at נגעים Nega'im *nega'im* was the כהנים *Kohanim*. But it
is true that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says how would a כהן
*Kohen* go and look at נגעים Nega'im *nega'im* if he didn't know
the הלכה halacha. *halachah*? He'd have a rabbi come with him, tell
him the הלכה halacha *halachah* and then he would still say the
magic words. So even there you're
right there's being the rabbis are owning more and more of that,
but nevertheless the כהנים *Kohanim* would still formally do the role of
צרעת Tzara'at. *tzara'at* and the rabbis are doing the role of sitting
in בית דין Beis Din. *Beit Din*, of judging. So at the
same time they're quoting this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* which is equating the
two and is all about כהנים *Kohanim*, there's a tacit understanding that
now the rabbis have moved into the role of the בית דין
din *Beit Din* here and it's not the כהנים *Kohanim* doing that
role.
He's being very formalistic about it because let's say you've bad eyesight
and the guy who's eyesight in one eye is perfect eyesight in
one eye so you can still...
yeah that's an interesting question about לכל מראה *le-chol mareh* whether we
say- I'm not remembering a discussion about that offhand- whether we say
about somebody that has bad eyesight and very limited, would that still
be the
לכל מראה *le-chol mareh*?
A lot of people today have myopia of various degrees.
Right clearly it's hard to define exactly. Exactly. There's like by ותכהין
עיניו מראות *vatikhena einav mero'ot* there is a sense that you have
very poor eyesight but you're right it's hard to quantify. I've always,
as somebody that's needed glasses for almost my entire life, I've always
just been like can't understand how they could have lived for three
thousand years without glasses.
I don't know, I'd have to check, I'd have to check if
somebody with very poor eyesight but still vision in both eyes could
see צרעת Tzara'at *tzara'at*. I don't know. And they could also be
a דיין dayan.
*dayan* with bad eyesight.
A judge presumably yes because that's more of a formal... well again
if you make the comparison. So I'd have to see. I don't
remember offhand.
One of the arguments I've seen against having women rabbis is that
a rabbi has to be someone who at least in theory is
qualified for דיין Dayan. *dayan* and this is a disproof for that
because we clearly have blind rabbis.
Right and there is no basis for saying, I mean you could
say you might not be able to be a דיין *dayan* but
exactly, but there's no association with the role of rabbi and פסקנינג
*paskening* with whether you're able to be a דיין *dayan*. I will
talk about women in this regard in a minute after we get
through the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* but...
that's probably not meant this way but on a symbolic level it
could have some implication about whether a judge sees clearly
through both...
symbolically correct, yeah that is true. Okay, so let's take a look.
And I assume similar to the כהן *Kohen* that was schlepped along
the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham *Talmid Chacham* that was schlepped along with
the כהן *Kohen*, if your biggest תלמיד חכם *Talmid Chacham* was blind,
he might be... sitting there off to the side and advising the
judges without formally taking the role as a judge. I'm sure there
were ways to consult with people even if they couldn't formally be
on the בית דין. We'll see something like that in a minute
in תוספות, Tosafot, which is dealing with the women issue. So let's
take a look, let's read this a little bit further. So ומה,
Uma, where was I? שלא בסומא... Shalov Bitzuma... Okay, ומה הקיש נגעים
לריבים, Uma Kish Nega'im L'Rivim, and it makes the link the other
way as well. Looking at צרעת Tzara'at like a judge sitting in
judgment. מה ריבים שלא בקרובים, Mah Rivim Shelo Bi'Krovim, the same way
you cannot be a relative of the person being judged, אף נגעים
שלא בקרובים. Af Nega'im Shelo Bi'Krovim. You cannot be a... a relative
cannot look at his relative's צרעת. Tzara'at You need somebody who is
a non-relative. This is what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. Actually, interestingly,
the משנה Mishnah in a... very famous משנה Mishnah because it has
a very beautiful double entendre in נגעים Nega'im. says... says opposite of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Says, כל נגעים אדם רואה חוץ מנגעי עצמו.
Kol Nega'im Adam Roeh Chutz Mi'Nigei Atzmo. You can see anybody's צרעת
Tzara'at. except your own. Which actually of כל נגעים, Kol Nega'im, right,
you can see anybody's faults except your own. It's a very nice
little line. But anyway, but that actually means you can see the
נגעים negaim, of a relative, but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes the link of נגעים negaim to judgment
and vice versa, and therefore you cannot see the צרעת of a
relative. So now the... now it continues, the ברייתא. Baraita.
אם ריבים בשלושה אף נגעים בשלושה. Im Rivim Bi'Shlosha, Af Nega'im Bi'Shlosha.
Maybe the same way a court case requires three, maybe to judge
a צרעת requires three. ודינו, V'Dinu, and it makes sense. ממונו בשלושה
גופו לא כל שכן? Mamono Bi'Shlosha, Gufo Lo Kol Shekein? If to
take away my money, to make past judgment on my property, you
need three people. To pass judgment on me, myself, and to make
me a מצורע, Metzora, how much more so should you need three
people? תלמוד לומר, Talmud Lomar, the verse teaches, והובא אל אהרן הכהן
או אל אחד מבניו הכהנים. V'Huva El Aharon HaKohen O El Achad
Mi'Banav HaKohanim. You should be brought to Aharon the Kohen in singular
or one of the sons, the Kohanim. הא למדת, Ha Lamadata, you
see clearly from the פסוק שאפילו כהן אחד רואה את הנגעים. She'Afilu
Kohen Echad Roeh Et HaNega'im. That even one Kohen, that is explicit,
can see נגעים. negaim. But according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it
is... there are other ways in which it is somewhat formal and
arbitrary. That is true, that it is linked. And the idea that
you... now it's not completely arbitrary as was pointed out, you know,
obviously you could be... if you're a relative you might be inclined
to, you know, even subconsciously judge in a particular way that's not
the... you know, that's less than fully objective, even if it's just
about צרעת. And you could also understand, you know, as David said,
that even though, you know, it's not so needed, it is a
little needed to have full sight as a judge, and certainly symbolically,
so you can understand it. The irony, of course, is is that
we don't also extend that to the witness, and the witness certainly
you would think needs to have sight in both eyes, and that
is not. So this is according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that's
how this משנה Mishnah is being read. But the Rabbis might not
agree to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir about this link, and now we're
about to see that in the next bit. But does it make
a
difference if it's like קיבל עליו? Kibel Alav?
That might... yes, I mean, then you could always have basically a
binding arbitration which does not require to be go by the formal
rules. You could even allow relatives if it's a case of binding
arbitration. Let's take a look at a story here in the גמרא.
Gemara ההוא סמיא דהוה בשיבבותיה דרבי יוחנן. Hahu Sumya Dehava Be'Shivutei De'Rabbi
Yochanan.
There was a blind person. Now, as we're going to see, it's
not fully blind. Really means blind in one eye, that... that was
in the neighborhood, in the... town of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. דהוה
דיין דינא. Dehava Kadayan Dina.
He was actually sitting as a judge. They used him as a
judge. ולא קאמר ליה ולא מידי. V'Lo Kama Leh V'Lo Midi. And
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan did not intervene, he didn't say anything. So
the גמרא Gemara says: היכי עבדי הכי? Hechi Avdi Hachi? How could
he do this? ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה. Ve'Amar Rabbi Yochanan:
Halacha Ke'Stam Mishnah. And we rule like a סתם משנה. Stam Mishnah.
ותנן, U'Tnan, we have a סתם משנה Stam Mishnah that says, כל
הכשר לדון כשר להעיד, Kol Ha'Kasher Ladun Kasher Le'Hayid, anybody that can
be a judge can be a witness, ויש כשר להעיד ואין כשר
לדון, Ve'Yesh Kasher Le'Hayid Ve'Ein Kasher Ladun, and there... there are people
that can be a witness without being a judge. ואמרינן, Va'Amrinan, לאתויי
מאי? L'Atuyei Mai? We said, who's that... who's that משנה Mishnah referring
to? ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'Amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself
said, maybe there's some other reader of this משנה. Mishnah. Maybe we
can find some other person that can be a witness and can't
be a judge. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that the משנה
Mishnah means: לאתויי סומא באחד מעיניו. L'Atuyei Suma Be'Achad Me'Einav. He says
the משנה Mishnah is referring to somebody who's blind in one eye.
So according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, this סתם משנה Stam Mishnah
is telling you like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that somebody blind in
one eye cannot be a judge. How did he therefore let this
person, who presumably was blind in one eye, be a judge in
his... in his neighborhood? This משנה Mishnah according to him is explicitly
prohibiting that.
How could he have stopped him? Was he the...
A religious authority. That's the גמרא's Gemara assumption. That's the... which is
interesting, right, that... you know, it's an anonymous person who was the
judge, but he's like the Rabbi. It does sound like that the
people that they had in the cases being the דיינים Dayanim were
not necessarily the like biggest of the rabbinical authorities, you know. So...
If people accept the judge, then...
Well, that could be an answer. That they... they explicitly stipulated like
Michael said. But the assumption here is, is that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan was clearly the religious authority in the town and he could
have intervened and he didn't. Why not? If according to him it's
exactly what our משנה Mishnah means. So the גמרא Gemara, says: רבי
יוחנן... רבי יוחנן סתמא אחרינא אשכח. Rabbi Yochanan stama achrina ashkhach. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan found another סתם משנה stam Mishna to rely on
that it's okay. No, there's a debate of סתם משניות. stam mishnayos.
This סתם משנה stam Mishna says one blind in one eye no
good, he has another סתם משנה stam Mishna says good. דתנן, detnan,
we taught in the משנה Mishna in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, דיני ממונות דנין
ביום וגומרין בלילה, dinei mamonos danin bayom vegomrin balaila, that you can
judge דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, you can start at the day and
finish at night.
So that obviously proves that blind in one eye is okay.
No, that's not what it's based on. It's based on that if
you link to נגעים, negaim, the first thing we said we learned
from the link to נגעים negaim. is that it can only be
during the day. And the גמרא Gemara assumes that that means that
it even has to conclude during the day. Any part of the
judgment has to be during the day. So since this משנה Mishna
says that you can have the judgment at least end at night,
it shows that we are not making a tight link to נגעים.
And since we're not making a tight link to נגעים, then there's
no basis to exclude somebody blind in one eye. So it doesn't
sound like the strongest counter-proof, but on the other hand, remember our
משנה Mishna wasn't explicit about blind in one eye either. So anyway,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan feels that that משנה Mishna indicates a non-רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir position. You don't link to נגעים. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ומאי ומד האי סתמא מהאי סתמא, umai umada hai stama
mehai stama, what makes one סתם משנה stam Mishna better than another
סתם משנה? stam Mishna? איבעית אימא, iba'is eima, סתמא דרבי מאיר, stama
deRabbi Meir,
number one is we know that our סתם משנה stam Mishna is
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So even though we would go by it,
although it's an individual opinion, a דעת יחיד, daas yachid, because it's
סתם, stam, but if we have another סתם, stam, then we know
that one סתם stam is backed by an individual, another סתם stam
is backed by a majority position. In that case, we go back
to our general rule: you go by the majority against רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, so you go against רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ואיבעית אימא,
ve'iba'is eima, if you want I could say משום דתני לה גבי
הלכתא דדייני. mishum detani lah gabi hilchesa dedayni. Or דדיני. dedini. So
this is a very important ruling about determining how we פסקן הלכה
pasken halacha when there's a contradiction of סוגיות sugyos or so on,
which is you are much more inclined to rule like the discussion
which is in the
appropriate context. So if here in נדה Nidda we have a משנה
Mishna that talks about who can be a good judge and then
in סנהדרין Sanhedrin we have a משנה Mishna that discusses the criteria
of judges, we're going to be much more inclined if there's a
contradiction to weigh in favor of the discussion in the right place
rather than in a discussion that is just by some digression found
its way into מסכת נדה. Masechet Nidda. So presumably when you're focusing
on the issue of judges you're going to be much more precise
and therefore that סוגיא sugya or that משנה Mishna has greater weight.
And this is a principle that is often used by the ראשונים.
Rishonim. If there's a contradiction of סוגיות, sugyos, to say we're going
to weigh much more in favor of a סוגיא, sugya, not always,
but as an inclination, in favor of a סוגיא sugya that is
in the appropriate
location of those laws rather than one that is there just by
digression. Now of course it could have said like Reuven and Michael
are saying, that maybe it was a special case, that he was
accepted as binding arbitration. But the גמרא Gemara didn't understand that to
be the case. So therefore it said that he ruled like this
other משנה, Mishna, which then means that according to this you can
be blind in one eye and be a judge. What about blind
in both eyes? So תוספות Tosafot actually says very interestingly, maybe? Maybe
according to the rabbis that argue on רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the
exact flip of what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, that if you're
a witness, blind in one eye is okay, blind in two eyes
is totally not good, that I told you at the beginning. But
maybe according to the rabbis that argue on רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
maybe a judge can be blind in both eyes? Right, once you
don't have this link and once we know that practically there's really
not such a need to be able to see as much for
judges as witnesses and you don't have a פסוק like witness you
say או ראה. o ra'ah. So תוספות Tosafot actually says that according
to the conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara it could be the exact
reverse. It could be that a witness, one eye, as we've always
been saying, blind in both eyes is no good, blind in one
eye is okay, and a judge may be even blind in both
eyes could be good. Pretty interesting possible conclusion. ורבי מאיר היא. veRabbi
Meir hi. Now I want to take a look at כל הכשר
לדון כשר להעיד kol haksher ladun kasher le'haid which deals with the
very famous תוספות Tosafot that deals with the question about women. So
let's take a look at this תוספות. Tosafot. So תוספות Tosafot says
the following. ואם תאמר, ve'im tomar, דאשה כשרה לדון. de'isha kesheira ladun.
תוספות Tosafot takes for granted that a woman could be a judge.
How does he take that for granted?
דכתיב בדבורה, dechesiv biDevorah, it says by Deborah, והיא שפטה את ישראל,
vehi shofta es Yisrael, she judged Israel. And again it's funny because
we would say פשט pshat in all of the book of שופטים
shoftim that they were political heads, not that they were actually sitting
in court cases. But the גמרא Gemara often seems to assume that
those שופטים shoftim were also the שופטים shoftim in the narrow sense
of sitting in court cases. So דבורה Devorah here was a שופטת
את ישראל. shofta es Yisrael. She was a judge, so presumably women
can be judges. ובפרק קמא דבבא קמא, uveperek kama deBava Kama, and
here's another proof that a woman could be a judge: דרשינן, darshinan,
we make a דרשה drasha in בבא קמא, Bava Kama, אשר תשים
לפניהם, asher tasim lifneihem, that these are the laws that you give
to them.
השוה הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל דינים שבתורה, hishvah haksasuv isha le'ish lechol
dinim shebatorah, that the laws apply to men and women equally. We
quoted that a similar דרשה drasha earlier. Not and here in בבא
קמא Bava Kama it's telling you not only do the sort of
prohibitions apply to men and women equally, the civil laws apply to
men and women equally. So it says לפניהם lifneihem includes women. So
that's in terms of them as being
the... The same way that verse refers to people who are judged,
it also refers to the judges, כדי שנו במכילתא לפניהם ולא לפני
עובדי כוכבים. k'dei shinu b'Mechilta lifneihem v'lo lifnei ovdei kochavim. So therefore
תוספות Tosafot says, look, number
one you have דבורה, Devorah, number two the verse of אשר תשים
לפניהם asher tasim lifneihem applies to women, and presumably if it applies
to women as being judged, it applies to women as being judges.
So women can be judges. But they can't be witnesses. So what
about the principle that anybody who can be a judge can be
a witness? ואישה פסולה, v'isha pesulah, we know a woman can't be
a witness, כדתנן בפרק קמא. k'detnan b'perek kamma. Right, certain cases they
can, and you know by איסור issur and other types of cases,
but in terms of the most formal עדות edut they cannot. So
how does that fit this rule? So תוספות Tosafot says, ויש לומר
דהכי קאמר, v'yesh lomar d'hachi ka'amar, here's how to read it: כל
איש הכשר לדון כשר להעיד. kol ish hakesher ladun kasher l'ha'id. Okay,
when we're talking about men, anybody that can be a judge can
be a witness. But you know what? When we're talking about women,
that's not true. By women, a woman could be a judge even
though she can't be a witness. So here תוספות Tosafot actually says
that yes, a woman can be a judge and that is a
position of ראשונים, Rishonim, that women can actually be דיינים. dayanim. And
then תוספות Tosafot says, ואינמי, v'inami, or you could say, דהאי דנידונים
הוי אישה בכלל, d'hai d'nidunim havei isha b'chlal, although women are judged,
מכל מקום בדיינים אין אישה בכלל, mi-kol makom b'dayanim ein isha b'chlal,
she's not in the category of being a judge, and the verse
you can't learn it from that verse of אשר תשים לפניהם. asher
tasim lifneihem. Now how about דבורה? Devorah? ודבורה היתה
דנה על פי הדיבור. u'Devorah hayta dana al pi hadibbur. דבורה Devorah
was like, you know, it was a special גזירת הכתוב, gezeirat hakatuv,
it was a special divine right that she had to judge. So
it was a special case, you can't learn out from it. אינמי,
Inami, or you could say, לא היתה דנה אלא מלמדת להם את
הדינים. lo hayta dana ela melamedet lahem et hadinim. She didn't actually
sit in cases. She would teach everybody the laws and then the
men would rule based on what she had taught. That's sort of
like I was trying to say. So she's the rabbi, yeah. So
she's right there, you go, she's the rabbi, she taught. So you
know, if you could have the blind person, he can tell the
judges what to say, like the תלמיד חכם tells the כהן what
to say. But the people who formally have to do it, they're
actually...
so שפטה shafta doesn't mean she judged, it means מלמדת, melamedet,
it means that she ultimately taught all the laws, but she wasn't
the person who actually sat in on the court cases. You could
have also said it meant that she was a political head. Okay,
but anyway she...
that a woman could be a ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva.
Right, exactly. So anyway, this תוספות Tosafot and other ראשונים Rishonim discuss
the same issue, but basically these are the two opinions that emerge
from the ראשונים. Rishonim. One is that a woman can be a
judge based on the evidence that תוספות Tosafot brings in the beginning,
and the rule that you have to be able to be a
witness to be a judge is not absolute, number one. And number
two is that,
what do you call it, that no, that a woman cannot be
a judge and דבורה Devorah was an exception for various reasons. Okay,
but that is, this is the distillation of the classic debate of
ראשונים Rishonim about how to understand the situation of דבורה Devorah and
whether a woman could be a judge. I should say, by the
way, that based on the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara in terms
of, you know, that a judge can be blind in one eye,
and תוספות Tosafot says maybe even blind in both eyes, you would
also have an exception to that rule. You could have somebody that
could be a judge, blind in both eyes, and couldn't be a
witness. So we might not, you know, but that at least we
say, we might not rule like the משנה. mishnah. תוספות Tosafot is
saying that point with the assumption that we do rule like this
משנה, mishnah, and therefore he has to deal with this question about
דבורה Devorah and he has his two conclusions about whether women can
be a judge. Okay. Yes.
So תוספות Tosafot doesn't consider the שופט shofet in the ספר sefer
and the נ"ך Nach in the דין does not necessarily mean a
דיין.
Right,
well that's sort of what I started with, that obviously פשט pshat
in the פסוקים pesukim is that it means political head and not
a judge, although the גמרא Gemaras. sometimes does it. The גמרא Gemara
sort of says, you know, כשמואל בדורו כיפתח בדורו, k'Shmuel b'doro k'Yiftach
b'doro, השופט אשר יהיה בימים ההם. hashofet asher yihye bayamim hahem. Now
since when was יפתח Yiftach sitting in court cases? Actually, given how
he ruled about his own נדר, neder, I wouldn't sit him on
any court cases.
I wouldn't ask him a שאלה.
she'ela. Right. Anyway, so he's following the rabbinic sort of lens to
read these שופטים as judges. Yes, but obviously that is an answer.
I should also say, by the way, some ראשונים Rishonim ask based
on this story of דבורה Devorah that the רמב"ם, Rambam, as you
might be aware, the רמבּ"ם Rambam says this idea of שררה, serarah,
of positions of authority, he applies that limit to women as well,
and the גמרא Gemara is not about women, and some ask on
him exactly from this case of דבורה, Devorah, right? Because you see
here obviously women had and that really is a case about political
authority, real authority, you know, not just the limited understanding in terms
of being a judge. Okay, so that is fascinating in terms of...
Yes.
They're like to testify that somebody died, allowing the wife
to remarry.
Right, yes. She should be able to be a judge if she
can be a witness in a particular area.
Well, no, we don't say exactly, the משנה mishnah says it's not
true that whoever can be a witness can be a judge, you
know, and so the issue about whether a woman could be a
judge, and there it's actually not formally a witness. There, when women
testify and it works, it's more because it's based on treating it
as evidence rather
than... So those cases exactly the point is that a woman cannot
be formally recognized as a witness, but we can accept what she
says and treat it as evidence on which we
would...
Right, correct. Absolutely. Correct.
I understand, but it doesn't mean that you can... right, but you
can't necessarily extrapolate from that to cases of, you know, a formal
בית דין. That ultimately boils down to, you know, how you... you
know, the independent discussion that the ראשונים Rishonim have about, based on
the evidence about women as דיין.
Yes, two questions...
I just have one question. Rav Uziel's famous תשובה Teshuvah about women
voting says that a woman can be a judge in דיני ממונות
Dinei Mamonos only if the parties accept her. Correct. So where does
this...
well, no, he means all the ראשונים Rishonim would agree to that
case. Yeah, this תוספות Tosafos assumes that the first answer of תוספות
Tosafos says yeah, woman can be just as eligible as a judge
as a man. And what Rav Uziel was saying is that it's
sort of like what Michael and Rivkah suggested about the person that
was blind here, which is that everybody agrees that if somebody is
accepted upon the parties as binding arbitration that then they can play
that role. Okay, let's take a look now at the next משנה.
Mishnah. כל
שחייב במעשרות מטמא טומאת אוכלין. Kol she-chayav be-ma'asros metamei tum'as ochlin. Anything
that's obligated in מעשרות Ma'asros can become טמא tamei as food, because
one of the key criteria for becoming for מעשר Ma'aser is that
it has to be considered food. ויש שמטמא טומאת אוכלין ואינו חייב
במעשרות. Veyesh she-metamei tum'as ochlin ve-eino chayav be-ma'asros. There are things that
can become טמא tamei as food are
food and can't be מעשר. Ma'aser. And what are those things? So
the גמרא Gemara right always gives you like this is one of
the shortest גמרא. Gemara לאתויי מאי? L'asuyei mai? This is literally six
words here. לאתויי בשר ודגים וביצים. L'asuyei basar ve-dagim ve-beitzim. Meat and
fish and eggs. There're plenty of things that are food that don't
grow from the ground and therefore are not חייב chayav in מעשר.
Ma'aser. פשיטא. Peshita. What?
פשיטא. Peshita. פשיטא, Peshita, yes, I know. Okay, כל kol next one.
כל שחייב בפאה חייב במעשרות. Kol she-chayav be-Peah chayav be-ma'asros. Anything obligated
in פאה Peah is obligated in מעשר. Ma'aser. ויש שחייב במעשרות ואינו
חייב בפאה. Veyesh she-chayav be-ma'asros ve-eino chayav be-Peah. There are things that
are obligated in מעשר Ma'aser and not פאה. Peah. פאה Peah has
more criteria than מעשר. Ma'aser. Why? Or what first, and then we
can say why. So the גמרא Gemara says לאתויי מאי? L'asuyei mai?
What are these things that are obligated in מעשר Ma'aser and not
פאה? Peah? לאתויי תאינה וירק. L'asuyei te-eina ve-yerek. Figs and vegetables, שאינו
חייב בפאה, she-eino chayav be-Peah, that you're not obligated in פאה. Peah.
Why not? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in a משנה Mishnah in פאה.
Peah. כלל אמרו בפאה. Klal amru be-Peah. They said a general principle
by פאה. Peah. כל שהוא אוכל, Kol she-hu ochel, anything that is
number one food, ונשמר, venishmar, it is protected, it's in your field
and it is protected, it's not like you let anybody come and
take it, okay, basically it's not הפקר, hefker, וגידולו מן הארץ, vegidulo
min ha-aretz, and it grows from the ground,
ולקיטתו כאחד, ve-lekitato ke-echad, and it is all gathered at one harvest
time of harvest, it's not a little bit today and a little
bit in a month from now and so on, ומכניסו לקיום, u-machniso
l'kiyum, and you can actually store it, it's not perishable, those things
are חייב בפאה chayav be-Peah or obligated in פאה. Peah. Now, let's
see what they exclude. אוכל, Ochel, food, למעט ספיחי סיטים וקוצה, lema'et
sefichei sitim ve-kotza,
to exclude like the remnants of סיטים וקוצה, sitim ve-kotza, which are
various plants which were used for dyes, so they were used for
obviously industrial and purposes, they weren't waste, but nevertheless they weren't food,
you might you might actually have a whole field where you're growing
this stuff because you're going to use it for a dye, but
nevertheless it's not food, so there's no obligation of פאה. Peah. That
is אוכל. ochel.
ונשמר, Venishmar, it's protected, למעט הפקר, lema'et hefker, to exclude things that
you don't really care let people come and take it, what do
you care it's barely worth anything, that would not be obligated. וגידולו
מן הארץ, Vegidulo min ha-aretz, it grows from the ground, למעט כמהין
ופטריות, lema'et kmeihin u-fatriyos, to exclude fungi and mushrooms, although they are
attached to the ground they do not grow from the ground, they
are a fungus,
fungi. ולקיטתו כאחד, Ve-lekitato ke-echad, and they are harvested at once, למעט
תאינה, lema'et te-eina, that excludes figs, figs ripen at different times and
they're harvested at various times. ומכניסו לקיום, U-machniso l'kiyum, one minute, and
you can store them for a long time, they are not perishable,
למעט ירק, lema'et yerek, to exclude vegetables, vegetables are perishable. So those
are the criteria for פאה. Peah. ואילו גבי מעשר, Ve-ilu gabi ma'aser,
but when it comes to מעשר, Ma'aser, תנן, tnan, our משנה Mishnah
in מעשרות Ma'asros says, it's actually quite very lovely what the גמרא
Gemara is doing, it's taking one of the first משניות mishnayos in
פאה, Peah,
one of the first משניות mishnayos in מעשרות, Ma'asros, putting them side
by side and saying look, the list of criteria is longer in
פאה Peah than it is by מעשר. Ma'aser. In מעשר Ma'aser you
don't have the last two criteria. Here's the first משנה Mishnah in
מעשרות. Ma'asros. כל
שהוא אוכל, Kol she-hu ochel, anything that's food, ונשמר, ve-nishmar, and protected,
וגידולו מן הארץ, ve-gidulo min ha-aretz, and grows from the ground, חייב
במעשרות, chayav be-ma'asros, but it did not have the last two criteria.
ואילו לקיטתו כאחד, Ve-ilu lekitato ke-echad, but harvested as one in one,
you know, at one time, ומכניסו לקיום, u-machniso l'kiyum, and put so
and and instead and and you know gathered for storage, לא קתני,
lo katani, is not in that list of criteria. So therefore what
do you see? You see that פאה Peah there are things
that
are... If something is not harvested as once, like figs, or cannot
be stored for long periods of time like vegetables, then it is
exempt from פאה Pe'ah and it is still obligated in מעשר. Ma'aser.
That's the ruling that פאה Pe'ah has greater criteria, so there are
things that are חייב chayav in מעשר Ma'aser that are not, remnant,
that are not חייב chayav in פאה, Pe'ah, figs and vegetables. Now,
what is the reason for the difference? So רש"י Rashi says, well,
the reason for the criteria by פאה Pe'ah is because we're making
it sort of like grain, and these two last criteria are classic
attributes of grain. You do harvest at one time and you also
store grain. Okay, so okay, so that's what רש"י Rashi says. As
opposed to מעשרות Ma'asros because, so it has to be like grain.
But fine, תוספות Tosafos says okay, but if that's the model, grain,
and that's fundamentally what the תורה talks about anyway, it says דגן
תירוש ויצהר, Dagan tirosh veyitzhar, you know, which is
grain, oil, and wine, grain, wine, and oil. So if that's the
model, so if we apply that to פאה, Pe'ah, we should apply
it to מעשר Ma'aser as well. Why don't we have those criteria
for מעשר? Ma'aser? So תוספות Tosafos has a beautiful answer. תוספות Tosafos
says that פאה, Pe'ah, the עניים ani'im have to be hovering around
waiting for you to finish so they can go get the פאה.
Pe'ah. Right? מעשרות, Ma'asros, they're not hovering around, you know, you have
to process the whole thing and then you take the מעשרות Ma'asros
and then you go and you distribute it. So תוספות Tosafos says
if you are, if this is a type of a thing which,
which they're going to, they did not want the עניים ani'im to
be wasting their time hovering around and waiting for you to finish
harvesting something that you only harvest piecemeal and that they would then
lose out the opportunity to go and get, you know, other פאהs
Pe'ahs somewhere else. So you could say well, let them make their
own judgment, but you know, so it is being a little paternalistic
of חז"ל, Chazal but okay, sometimes you as if you're making the
rules for society, you have to realize that people, you know, you
have to be a little paternalistic, you might realize that people will
not make always the best decisions for themselves. So they actually wanted
to say that this is going to be exempt, because if it's
obligated, they felt that the עניים ani'im would sort of hover, you
know, around in these cases and pass up better opportunities for collecting
the פאה, Pe'ah, and that was not a concern when it came
to מעשרות Ma'asros because anyway they wouldn't be hovering when it came,
when it came to מעשרות. Ma'asros. So that's at least the answer
that תוספות Tosafos gives. But whatever explanation you give, what is important
to note is that both רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos say that
none of these things are biblically obligated in מעשרות, Ma'asros, in terms
of vegetables or figs. Biblically, the only thing obligated in מעשרות Ma'asros
and פאה Pe'ah is, according to רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos here
agree, דגן תירוש ויצהר, Dagan tirosh veyitzhar, grain, oil, and, what do
you call it, and, and grain, wine, and oil. That is somewhat
debated. Some ראשונים Rishonim do think that other fruit might be obligated,
that it's not limited to, it certainly doesn't include vegetables. Everybody agrees
vegetables is rabbinic. There is some debate about whether fruit, other than
grapes and olives, are biblical or not. But רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafos here say that they are not. The only thing is grain,
fruits, and olives, and that all of this is rabbinic. And even
so, I mean, grain, wine, right, right, grain, wine, and oil. But
all of this, so anyway any discussion about figs and about vegetables
is all a rabbinic discussion. And nevertheless, by פאה Pe'ah we model
it after grain and we say that it has to have all
those criteria, and it's a more limited subset. And by מעשרות Ma'asros
we don't model it off of after grain, and it's a much
bigger category and it includes vegetables and figs and the like. Yes.
I want to understand. So olives, right? Now olives, oil you give
the מעשר Ma'aser on, but the actual olives you give the מעשר
Ma'aser on because it's נכתף כאחד, niktif ke'echad, right? Because don't the
ones on the top of the tree ripen first, and isn't that
what they did?
They would like harvest those? Yeah, I don't know exactly what range
like of a few weeks is considered נכתף כאחד, niktif ke'echad, that
I don't know. Meaning, I think we're talking about like throughout the
year as opposed to...
Wait, do olives really ripen throughout the year?
I have no idea. I have no idea either. Somebody could look
it up on Wikipedia.
Yeah, so would olives, you do say that you give פאה Pe'ah
on olives?
For רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos that says it's only דגן תירוש
ויצהר, Dagan tirosh veyitzhar, would it apply to grapes and olives if
you did not turn them into oil and wine? I don't think
so. I don't think so.
Meaning you wouldn't give פאה? Pe'ah?
You would not דאורייתא. d'oraisa. No, דרבנן d'rabbanan you do, by all
this stuff. דרבנן d'rabbanan the criteria is right, but דאורייתא d'oraisa I
think it's only oil, it's only oil and wine, not grapes and
olives.
Yeah. Raw olives are inedible, so they wouldn't be, you couldn't even
take מעשר Ma'aser from them yet.
What do you mean? You mean when we buy olives in the
thing,
they've been, they have to be cured?
Oh, really? Okay. Raw olives are completely inedible. Learn something new every
day. Okay.
I always thought that fruit decomposes faster than vegetables. Really?
Well, you can also dry fruit. חז"ל Chazal. are always talking about,
about sort of, you know, drying out your fruit, creating dried fruit.
You create dried vegetables?
I mean, yeah.
What do you... yeah, yeah. Really?
Like what?
Give me an example of a dried vegetable. Dehydrated?
I mean, like dried tomatoes?
Oh, sun-dried... Sundried tomatoes are fruits.
I mean, the חז"ל.
Okay, that's true. Okay, anyway.
Philosophical thing here also when it comes to things that are not
לקיטתו כאחד, lakitato k'echad, how do you know if the guy left
it as פאה pe'ah or left it because it wasn't ripe yet?
That's an interesting question too, right. Although by פאה pe'ah it would
more be, I mean that you would have harvested everything except one
section, so it's לקיטתו כאחד, lakitato k'echad, you know, it wouldn't be
sort of which is more sort of distributed. Anyway, so okay let's
just by the way I'll read you that one line of תוספות,
Tosafot, it's like six lines from the bottom and ואומר רבינו תם
v'omer Rabbeinu Tam starts the line. משום דתאנה אין לקיטתה כאחד mishum
d'te'einah ein lakitatah k'echad הלכך לא גזרו חכמים בפאה בה, hilkach lo
gazru Chachamim b'pe'ah bah, they didn't want to obligate you in פאה
pe'ah for that. שלא יצפו עניים מתי יגמור בעל הבית לקיטתו, shelo
yetzap'u aniyim matay yigmor ba'al habayit lakitatah, they'll hang around waiting for
you to finish, ויפסידו יותר ממקום אחר ממה שירויחו בפאה זו v'yafsidu
yoter mimakom acher mimah sheyarvichu b'pe'ah zo
and they'll wait and they'll have lost more because they could have
been going to other places and they'll be hanging around and it
won't be in their best interest. אי בירק נמי, in b'yarak nami,
how about vegetables? That is one time, so why did they not
obligate you in vegetables? אין הפאה חשובה. ein hape'ah chashuvah.
So vegetables is not such a big haul, you know, in terms
of value. ואינו שוה אלא מעט v'eino shaveh ela m'at and it's
only worth a little, ואם ימתינו אחריו עד הערב יפסידו יותר. v'im
yamtinu acharev ad ha'erev yafsidu yoter. Better to go somewhere else. So
actually it's quite fascinating, you know, it does raise questions. You know,
some people here might not agree with this type of a paternalist
approach, but obviously that is sometimes what informs certain
תקנות. takkanot. Well, that's true. Okay, anyway, that is תוספות's Tosafot explanation.
But again the key is
לקיטתו כאחד, lakitato k'echad, you know, that's
an interesting example.
Right, and they don't, and they don't,
they wait for apartment buildings. Ah, but they know the right time.
It is לקיטתו כאחד. lakitato k'echad. That's a very good example, correct,
right. They're not gathering it one by one. Okay, so there it
is. It's modeled, פאה's pe'ah much more closely modeled after grain and
has those additional criteria. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. אם היו בהם
שומים ובצלים,
im hayu bahem
shumim u'vitzalim, now we go on to say that if actually
there were, what do you call it, a garlic and onion amongst
the vegetables, חייבין, chayavin, then they're, now, it doesn't mean that the
other vegetables are חייב, chayav, but at least garlic, not all vegetables
are excluded, garlic and onions actually is מכניסו לקיום, machnisu l'kiyum, right,
garlic and onions does last for a much longer time. Except in
my kitchen it always, they always start growing, what do those onions
grow? Sprout. Sprout. I, takes me so long to eat them. Anyway,
I gotta start buying in smaller quantities. דתנן, detnan, we taught in
a משנה: Mishnah: מלבנות בצלים שבין הירק, malbinot b'tzalim she'bein hayarak, if
you have rows of onions between your vegetable rows, רבי יוסי אומר
פאה מכל אחת ואחת. Rabbi Yosei omer pe'ah mikol achat v'achat. You
take פאה pe'ah for each set. So you do, you have your
like you know cucumbers onions, cucumbers onions in strips. So how many,
is it one field of onions and you take one פאה pe'ah
or is each row seen as a different field of onions and
you take, have to leave a corner of each row? So רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosei says פאה מכל אחת ואחת, pe'ah mikol achat v'achat,
you leave פאה pe'ah from each row, וחכמים אומרים מאחת על הכל.
v'Chachamim omrim mei'achat al hakol. No, you look at it all as
one big field of onions and you just leave one פאה. pe'ah.
So the debate is do you look at it as one or
as many? But what they don't debate is that onions are חייב
בפאה chayav b'pe'ah because onions would be an example of a vegetable
that at, that you would actually store and therefore it is obligated
in פאה. pe'ah. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, so now he says in
the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, עולשין שזרען מתחלה לבהמה. ulshin
shezara'an mitechilah l'beheimah.
If you have a certain type of a grass, עולשין, ulshin, I
have no idea what type of grass that is, that you planted
it initially for animals. Presumably this is something that in an rare
exception you could use for human food but primarily was not. Whatever
the case is, you planted it. What?
Alfalfa. Alfalfa. Okay, you planted it and
you were planning on using it to feed your cows with it.
You were going to harvest it for your cows and therefore it
would not be considered food. Food is only something in terms of
טומאה tum'ah of food that is for human consumption. ונמלך עליהם לאדם,
v'nimlach aleihem l'adam, and then as they were growing you said, you
know what, I actually think I'm going to harvest it for people
food. Will it be considered food for the purpose of becoming able
to become טמא? tamei? So let's take a look. צריכה מחשבה לכשינתלשו.
tzerichah machshavah l'cheshiyitlishu. Your intention of making it human food is not
enough to change its status as food when it's growing, because since
it cannot become טמא, tamei, this is for the purpose of becoming
טמא, tamei, since it cannot become טמא tamei when it's growing, its
identity and its status cannot change when it's growing. Only after you
harvest it and then you planned on using it for human food,
then does its status change, but not while it is growing. קסבר,
kasavar, he's of the opinion, מחשבת חיבור לא שמה מחשבה. machshevet chibur
lo shemah machshavah. Intention of something that is attached is not considered
intention, does not change its status because since it can't become טמא
tamei when it's attached, its status cannot be defined differently also when
it is attached for that purpose. אמר רבא אף אנן נמי תנינא.
amar Rava af anan nami tanina. We taught similarly in a משנה
Mishnah in טהרות. Taharot. שלשה עשר דברים נאמרו בנבלת עוף הטהור. shloshah
asar devarim neemru b'neveilat of hatahor. Thirteen laws were said about the
carcass of a... dead bird. Remember the famous carcass of a dead
bird that what? When you swallow it, you become טמא, tamei, but
not when you touch it? Okay, but there are thirteen laws about
it. וזו אחת מהן, V'zo achat meihen, here's one of them: צריכה
מחשבה tsrichah machshavah ואינה צריכה הכשר. v'einah tsrichah hechsheir. If you want
it to become טמא tamei not just when you swallow it, but
to become טמא tamei when you touch it, that's only if you
plan on using it for food. Hopefully for a non-Jew because you're
not allowed to eat it. But if you plan on using it
as human food, then it will become considered טמא tamei as food
and even by touch and not by swallowing. Now, by the way,
how does it become טמא? tamei? Here's a very fascinating הלכה. Normally,
if food to become טמא tamei needs two things. Number one, it
has to be made susceptible, has to be in contact with a
liquid. And number two, something טמא tamei has to touch it. Because
this thing in itself can be a source of טומאה tumah if
it is swallowed, so that means that it basically leapfrogs over the
requirements of becoming טמא tamei as food, as conducting טומאה. tumah. So
it a) does not need to have liquid come in contact with
it, does not need to be made susceptible. And number two, perhaps
even more surprising, doesn't have to come in contact with another טמא
tamei thing. It itself is טמא. tamei. So why would it need
to become contact with something else? Now, it will only communicate its
טומאה tumah when swallowed, but the very fact that it can, under
the right circumstances, be a source of טומאה, tumah, means is enough
for it to essentially receive its own טומאה tumah and become טמא
tamei as not an אב av but as a ראשון rishon without
touching anything else, without הכשר. hechsheir. So that is the law of
אינה צריכה הכשר, einah tsrichah hechsheir, does not need liquid, does not
need to touch, but only once you consider it a food, only
once you plan on eating. Okay, so now what does this prove?
So let's take a look. אלמא מחשבת חיים לא שמה מחשבה. Alma
machshevet chayim lo shma machshavah. It says you have to plan on
eating it. Now, presumably, we're talking about a chicken in your yard
died. So you were planning on שחיטה shechting that chicken and then
it just died on you. So why do you need to plan
to treat it as food? You were thinking about that when it
was alive and around and clucking, you were thinking you were going
to שחיטה shecht it. So you see that your intention when it
was alive doesn't count. And that's by analogy. So what's the analogy?
הכא נמי מחשבת חיבור לא שמה מחשבה. Hacha nami machshevet chibur lo
shma machshavah. When your intention about something as food when it's connected
to the ground also doesn't count. And the logic is the same.
Since right now as a live chicken it cannot become טמא, tamei,
the way you define it as food is not meaningful. Since when
something is connected to the ground it cannot become טמא, tamei, the
way you define it as food is not meaningful. So that is
רבא's Rava proof. You see that your definition of something as food
is only meaningful when it can become טמא. tamei. When it's dead,
when it's not connected to the ground. Why didn't it matter why
you planted it? No, but if at the time of planting you
were intending, then sort of your definition was before it became connected
to the ground, it was, you know, you had seeds and, you
know, that would still, that would be meaningful because then it preceded
being actually grown from the ground. Okay, it was in with seeds,
before the seeds took root, then it's still meaningful. רבי זירא אמר
Rabbi Zeira amar no, Rabbi Zeira says that's not a proof. הכא
בגוזל שנפל מן האגם עסקינן. Hacha b'gozal shenafal min ha'agam askinan. We're
talking about that a bird dropped dead out of the sky. Without
talking about your chicken. Your chicken maybe would be like you already
intended to make it eat it and therefore you would not need
מחשבה. machshavah. We're talking about a pigeon dropped out of the sky
or somebody went pigeon hunting and something and there was no מחשבה
מחיים. machshavah m'chayim. ולא הוה קמן דנחשב לה. V'lo hava kaman d'neichshov
lah. It wasn't in front of us that we could have intended
when it was alive. Maybe intention when it's alive counts. This is
a special case. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, תרנגולת שביבנה מאי
איכא למימר. tarnegolet she'b'Yavneh mai ika l'meimar. We're going to see in
a few minutes a case where the rabbis try to prove the
issue about מחשבה, machshavah, whether you need intention or not, from a
story about a chicken in יבנה. Yavneh. The chicken of it's sort
of like the, you know, the גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin where
right now in the three weeks period, right, about the famous story
about the rooster whatever and then and the חורבן הבית. churban habayit.
People know that אגדתא aggadata in גיטין. Gittin. Anyway, so anyway here's
the chicken in יבנה. Yavneh. So how about the chicken in יבנה?
Yavneh? We're going to be discussing that in a minute. And presumably
if you're talking about a chicken, you're talking about a domesticated animal
that you had מחשבה machshavah when it was alive and it didn't
count and the whole discussion is going to be about מחשבה machshavah
afterwards. תרנגול הבר הוה. Tarnigol habar hava. Well, let's take a look.
הכא תרנגול הבר הוה. Hacha tarnigol habar hava. That was a wild
chicken. Same story. It was not a chicken that was clucking around
in your field. And therefore you did not have intention when it
was alive. אחיכו עליה. Achiku aleih. So they laughed on him, well,
that's a silly answer. Why did they laugh? They said תרנגול הבר
עוף טמא הוא. Tarnigol habar of tamei hu. A wild chicken is
a non-kosher bird. Now that's quite fascinating. The גמרא Gemara understands that
this idea of a wild chicken would actually refer to a different
species of chicken that did not that was maybe it was even
a predatory or whatever. Whatever it was, did not have non-kosher סימנים
simanim and was a different species. So the גמרא Gemara says well,
that can't be because then we're talking about נבלת עוף טהור niveilat
of tahor and that would be a carcass of a non-kosher bird
if these wild chickens were such a species. So the גמרא Gemara
says ועוף טמא מי מטמא? V'of tamei mi metamei? And a non-kosher
bird does not cause טומאה tumah when you swallow it? So therefore
we cannot be talking about that. We're talking about the carcass of
a kosher bird, not the carcass of a non-kosher bird. So this
was right, this was what רבי Rebbe so, so אביי Abaye said
back to them, גברא רבא אמר מילתא לא תחוכי ליה, Gavra rabba
amar milsa lo tichochei lei, a great person said something, don't laugh,
don't mock. Okay, you didn't like the answer that that was maybe
talking about a wild, about a wild chicken, but don't mock, there's
a way that could be a good answer. בתרנגולא דמרדא, Be-tarnigola de-marda,
we're not talking about a different species of chicken that's not kosher.
We're talking about a domesticated chicken and this one went and flew
off, and this one became a wild chicken, flew the coop. So
fine, that's the case. It's not a different species, it's still kosher.
ומאי ברא, U-mai bara, what do we mean by wild? דאיברי ממארי,
De-ivrei mi-marei, it freed itself from its master. Sure. What? Feral bird.
Feral. Oh, okay, good term, feral bird. So now what have we
said? We said the following. We're trying to prove that מחשבה machshava
when it's alive doesn't matter because you need מחשבה machshava when a
bird dies. And presumably it's been in your yard, so your מחשבה
machshava when it was alive didn't count. So the answer is, no,
maybe those are cases about wild birds that dropped out of the
sky.
What about the fact that we know one of those cases is
about a chicken?
So we're saying, fine, it's about a chicken that actually happened to
go off and to become wild on its own, but all those
cases maybe are not when you had מחשבה machshava alive, they're cases
about wild birds. Okay wait, so if a wild bird dropped out
of the sky then there's the case you're saying you need מחשבה?
machshava? There's one case about that, then you need מחשבה, machshava, otherwise
מחשבה machshava when it's alive would count. But if I'm going like
bird hunting, aren't I thinking about it when I'm... so that's interesting.
Is your מחשבה machshava meaningful if you have no control over it?
Maybe your מחשבה machshava isn't meaningful, right? Only what makes the fact
that you want to eat it meaningful if it's a wild bird,
only after maybe it's under your control. Okay, now the question that
רש"י Rashi though asks is, but I don't get it, if it
used to be in your yard clucking around, then you had מחשבה
machshava then. Why doesn't that stick? So you could say, sort of
like I'm saying for Michael, once it leaves your control, maybe your
designation is no longer meaningful. רש"י Rashi doesn't say that, he says,
רש"י Rashi actually says we would be talking about that after it
became feral it gave birth to chicks. So those chicks are again,
it's a kosher species, but not under your control. But רש"י Rashi
says the designation you gave it before it rebelled would have remained.
Anyway, that's the case. We're saying maybe your מחשבה machshava works and
these are cases about wild animals. רב פפא אמר תרנגולתא דאגמא הויא.
Rav Pappa amar tarnigolta de-agma hava. Okay, is this somehow better? It's
a species of chickens of the swamp. Sounds like a classic Far
Side cartoon, chickens of the swamp, right? Anyway, so presumably this was
a species of wild chickens that was kosher, but they were wild.
So that's the case. Yes again, it's not תרנגולא דברא. tarnigola de-bara.
Right, it's something that's not תרנגולא דברא, tarnigola de-bara, it's a kosher
species. רב פפא לטעמיה, Rav Pappa le-taimei, רב פפא Rav Pappa goes
according to his reasoning, דאמר רב פפא תרנגולא דאגמא אסיר, de-amar Rav
Pappa tarnigola de-agma assur, a rooster of the swamp is forbidden, תרנגולתא
דאגמא שריא, tarnigolta de-agma sharya, a hen of the swamp is permissible.
וסימנך, Ve-simancha, the way you remember it is, עמוני ולא עמונית, amoni
ve-lo amonit, okay, that the Amonite, the male Amonites are forbidden, not
the female, so these male chickens are forbidden, the roosters, not the
female. Now, what is this about? So תוספות Tosafos says, first thinks
that we're talking about the same species, and it's possible that the
male of a species would be non-kosher and the female of the
exact same species would be kosher, that maybe one would have the
non-kosher סימנים simanim and the other would not, and that you could
actually distinguish male and female. Then תוספות Tosafos rejects that, he says,
look, at the end of the day, it's not really about the
סימנים, simanim, it's really about the species and to figure out which
are the species that the תורה talks about. So תורה in the
end says that we're, תוספות Tosafos in the end says we're not
talking about, we're talking about two different species. One is called swamp
roosters, and the other's called swamp hens, but they're both full species,
they're not males versus females, like we say ladybugs. Right, you can
have male ladybugs. Okay, and you can have, what, female crawdaddies, I
guess, but anyway, what do they call them? Anyway, daddy longlegs. Anyway,
so, Spanish all cats are male. Okay, there you go. So anyway,
but it's fascinating, תוספות Tosafos thinks for a minute that actually one
species could be divided male and female, but in the end he
says, we're talking different species. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. דרש
מרימר, Darash Mareimar, מרימר Mareimar explicated, תרנגולתא דאגמא אסירא. tarnigolta de-agma asira.
So he said, he disagreed with רב פפא Rav Pappa and he
said even the swamp hens are forbidden. חזייהו רבנן דדרסה ואכלה Chazya
rabbanan de-darsa ve-achla because the Rabbis saw that it trampled and ate,
והיינו גיורתא, ve-hainu giyorta, and that's also the species called a גיורתא
giyorta which we know, we assume to be non-kosher. So this tells
us that one of the classic signs of non-kosher birds is that
they trample. Now what does trample mean? רש"י Rashi has two explanations.
One means it picks up their food and eats the food with
their claw as opposed to like pecks at their food. And the
other is that it actually holds down their food and that allows
them to eat part of it without picking up the rest. So
the fact that they're holding it down with a claw is also
in the category of דרסה darsa even if they're not like picking
it up with their hands. What? Eating with their, well right, it's
some form of eating with their hands. Anyway, very important in terms
of discussion of כשר kosher birds. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. Now back
to this issue about מחשבה machshava by bird when they're alive or
dead. גוזל שנפל לגת. Gozel shenafal l'gat. So a bird fell into
the wine vat. A כשר kosher bird, yeah. וחשב עליו להעלותו לכותי,
v'chashav alav l'haaloso l'kuti, and you figured that, okay, let me scoop
it out of the wine vat. It died obviously, and I'll give
it to my friend the non-Jew. Look, it'll be pre-, what do
you call that when you put stuff in liquid overnight? Marinated. Pre-marinated.
Okay, I'll give it to my friend the non-Jew. So is it
now considered to become food and therefore טמא? tamei? Remember, a dead
כשר kosher bird does not need contact with something else to be
טמא. tamei. Once you make it food, it automatically is טמא. tamei.
So now that it's dead, you are going to make it food,
you're going to give it as food to the non-Jew. So the
הלכה is: טמא! tamei! Then it is טמא. tamei. Clearly, you're going
to make it human food. After it's dead, it's going to be
therefore טמא. tamei. לכלב, L'kelev, if you want to feed it to
your dog, טהור, tahor, because it has to be human food. רבי
יוחנן בן נורי אומר אף לכלב טמא. Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer:
Af l'kelev tamei. Though even if you want to feed it to
your dog, not because he says normally it's enough to be considered
animal food, but because as we're going to see, he does not
require you to intend to make it food. Even without your מחשבה,
machshava, this will be considered
food and therefore it is always going to be טמא. tamei. So
basically מחשבה machshava is irrelevant. Correct. That's how the גמרא Gemara is
going to explain it. Not clear from what we've read so far,
but that's how the גמרא Gemara will explain it. אמר רבי יוחנן
בן נורי. Amar Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri. So Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri
says to the Rabbis: קל וחומר! Kal v'chomer! I'll make a קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. אם מטמא טומאה חמורה, Im m'tamei tuma chamura, if
this thing, if you were to swallow it, would have a heavy
טומאה, tuma, it would be an אב הטומאה, av hatuma, שלא במחשבה,
shelo b'machshava, without any intention, you just swallowed it, even if you
didn't realize you were eating it, you know, accidentally you ate it.
Nevertheless, without any intention, if you're swallowing it, it is an אב
הטומאה. av hatuma. לא יטמא טומאה קלה שבמחשבה? Lo y'tamei tuma kala
shebo b'machshava? Then even without intention, it at least should be a
ראשון. rishon. Okay? Says, you know, to be an אב av you
don't need intention, so to be a ראשון rishon you shouldn't need
intention. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him: לא! Lo!
No. אם אמרת בטומאה חמורה שכן ירדה לכך. Im amarta b'tuma chamura
sheken yerdetta kach. If you say by heavy טומאה, tuma, an אב,
av, that's because it's not like in the פרשה, parsha, it's not
being about being food, it's not about its identity as food. So
therefore, you don't need to treat it as food. תאמר בטומאה קלה
שכן ירדה לכך? Tomar b'tuma kala sheken yerdetta kach? Will you say
it by this lighter טומאה, tuma, where it's all about its identity
as food? And if you don't intend to eat it or to
feed it to a non-Jew, it is not considered food. אמר להם,
Amar lahen, he said back to them: תרנגולת שביבנה תוכיח. Tarnegoles shebi-Yavne
tochiach. Now we see why we were talking about it. How about
the chicken in יבנה? Yavne? That was a case presumably that they
treated as טמא tamei even though there was no מחשבה. machshava. שירדה
לכך, She-yirdesa l'kach, for the case where they treated it as a
טומאה tuma of a ראשון rishon without being swallowed, as טמא tamei
as food, וטימאוה שלא במחשבה, v'timuah shelo b'machshava, and they made it
טמא tamei without anybody having intended to eat it. אמרו לו, Amru
lo, they said back to him: משם ראיה? Misham raya? You think
that's a proof? כותים היו שם. Kutim hayu sham. There were כותים,
Kutim, Samaritans, there. I haven't checked the text whether the original גרסא
girsa is נכרי Nochri or כותים, Kutim, because so far it's not
relevant that they're כותים, Kutim, Samaritans, just non-Jews. וחשבו עליה לאכילה. V'chishvu
aleha l'achila. מאי אית לך? Mai it lach? What do you have?
Does the שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz say whether the original text is different? No.
Okay. So actually, they were planning on eating it, so you can't
bring any proof from there. So here you have a debate whether
the נבילת עוף טהור neveilas of tahor requires מחשבה machshava or not.
But, what? There are various versions. Some say נכרים. Nochrim. I'm assuming,
because it's not relevant that it's כותים. Kutim. נכרי. Nochri. Yeah, it
makes sense. This has nothing to do with them being כותים, Kutim,
and normally the גמרא Gemara anyway normally considers כותים Kutim to be
Jews, at least most of the time anyway. So the answer here
is that what? That they're debating whether you need מחשבה. machshava. And
again, now you see why it was discussed earlier, because it was
a chicken. So why are they debating? You had מחשבה machshava when
it was alive. So either it was a wild chicken, or again,
this is a proof that מחשבה machshava when it's alive, which is
the simple read, doesn't matter. You need מחשבה machshava when it's dead.
That's what the Rabbis say. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbi Yochanan ben
Nuri disagrees. What about the case of the chicken that didn't need
מחשבה? machshava? They actually said people were planning on eating it, the
non-Jews were planning on eating it and therefore it did have מחשבה.
machshava. So now let's take a look at just the start of
the גמרא Gemara. about this. So the גמרא says like this: במאי
עסקינן? B'mai askinan? What are we talking about? אילימא בכרכין, Eleima b'krachin,
if you're talking about in the cities. In the cities, people would,
you know, there'd be a large population and people would also have
more bizarre tastes. So therefore, food, you didn't need as much מחשבה.
machshava. Even some type of things that normally weren't eaten would more
regularly be, in the villages, would be eaten in the cities. So
therefore, if it's in the city, למה לי מחשבה? lama li machshava?
Then who even needs מחשבה machshava for a dead bird, even if
it died unnaturally? People will eat it regardless. והתנן, V'hatnan, דתנינא משנה:
d'tanina mishneh: נבלת בהמה טהורה בכל מקום, Neveilas beheima tehora b'chol makom,
if you have the carcass, meaning a non-שחוטה shechted carcass of a
כשר kosher animal anywhere, whether city or village, even in villages they'll
eat that. ונבלת עוף טהור וחלב בכרכין, V'neveilas of tahor v'chelev b'krachin,
or the carcass of a כשר kosher bird or fat, again, we're
not talking about Jews eating it, non-Jews, in the cities, so those
are things that אין צריכין לא מחשבה ולא הכשר, ein tzrichin lo
machshava v'lo hechsher, don't need intention to eat, and therefore as we
said by these things... So they don't need הכשר hechsher since they're
themselves a source of טומאה, tumah, they automatically become טמא tamei by
themselves once they are considered food. So the basic point is that
some things don't need מחשבה machshavah because everybody will eat it, non-Jews
at least, you know, even if it's not kosher like dead carcasses
of cows. And there are some things that at least in the
cities they'll eat, like carcasses of birds. So if it's a city,
who needs מחשבה? machshavah? Everybody will eat it anyway. It's automatically food.
אלא בכפרים, Ella bekfarim, it must be talking about that you're in
the villages. And in the villages normally people don't eat carcasses of
birds and therefore it needs מחשבה. machshavah. So the גמרא says ולימא
למאן דאמר דלא בעי מחשבה? ve-leima le-man d'amar de-la ba'ei machshavah? So
who says, how could there be anybody who says you don't need
מחשבה machshavah in the villages? והתנן, Ve-hatnan, the משנה Mishnah says, נבלת
בהמה טמאה בכל מקום, nivlat behemah teme'ah be-chol makom, if it's a
carcass of a non-kosher animal, that's quite fascinating because we're talking about
non-Jews, we're talking about carcasses, and the משנה Mishnah still assumes that
non-Jews are more ready to eat carcasses of cows than they are
let's say carcasses of pigs, which is bizarre. I have no idea
why that's the assumption. Anyway, carcass of a non-kosher animal, ונבלת עוף
טהור בכפרים, ve-nivlat of tahor ba-kfarim, or the carcass of a bird
in the villages, those things are not normally considered food, even the
carcass of a pig in the city, and those things צריכה מחשבה,
tzrichah machshavah, you need intention, ואינה צריכה הכשר, ve-einah tzrichah hechsher, but
again once it's food it automatically becomes טמא. tamei. So the גמרא
says, look, the משנה Mishnah is clear. In the city, a carcass
of a bird doesn't need intention, it's automatically food. In a village,
the משנה Mishnah says it needs intention. So how could רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri say it doesn't need intention? If
it's a city, everybody agrees it doesn't need intention, and if it's
not in the city, then presumably everybody agrees it does need מחשבה.
machshavah. What's the debate? So we'll just read the answer, we'll pick
up with this tomorrow. אמר רבי זירא בר חנינא, Amar Rabbi Zeira
bar Chanina, לעולם בכרך, le'olam be-krach, we are talking about a city.
So if we're talking about a city, why did the rabbis say
it needed intention? דגיתו מאסתו ועשאו ככפר. degito me'asto va'asao ke-kfar.
And the vat made it disgusting and made it like a village,
which means the reason that they're having a debate here is it's
a city, normally you would not need intention, it would normally automatically
be food, which is רבי יוחנן בן נורי's Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
position. But the חכמים Chachamim say, look, it fell into this vat,
normal people aren't going to eat it, so in this case you
actually need intention, right? Somewhat a pre-marinating. And רבי יוחנן בן נורי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says
no, it still follows the general rule, it's in a city, it's
a dead bird, it does not need מחשבה machshavah to be considered
food. So we will pick up with this גמרא. Yes. Questions?
One...